בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Okay,
so today's דף daf is קיב. kuf yud bais. Okay, so קיב
kuf yud bais 112. We picked up on the very top of
קיב, kuf yud bais, three lines down. Right, we did that, right,
yesterday? מפתח חלוקא. mafteach chaluka. So just to review what we've done,
the משנה mishnah discussed, you know, that there were certain knots that
you were חייב chayav for, certain knots that were פטור אבל אסור,
patur aval asur, and certain knots that were מותר. muttar. So just
to refresh what רש"י Rashi said and tell you what the רמב"ם
Rambam says so you understand the basic approaches that there are here
in the ראשונים. Rishonim.
רש"י Rashi emphasized that a קשר של קיימא kesher shel kayama was
that it was meant that way to be permanent, forever. Like you
tie a thing around the loop for the boat or the loop
in the nose of the camel and you leave it that way
forever. So that's a קשר של קיימא. kesher shel kayama. That's the
only thing that's biblical. According to רש"י, Rashi, it's pretty hard to
transgress biblically. There is some question about, you know, how do you
define forever? Does it mean the type of knot that generally is
made forever regardless of whether it itself has that ability to stand
forever or whether that was your intention, the scope of your intention.
But anyway,
the basic definition is something that is made forever.
That's רש"י. Rashi. What is totally מותר muttar according to רש"י? Rashi?
Things like which is what we're going to focus on today, the
things like your shoes and your garments, the things that you regularly
do and undo. And I'll actually read you a רש"י Rashi on
the משנה. mishnah. רש"י Rashi says by מפתח חלוקא, mafteach chaluka, it's
like the last narrow line of רש"י Rashi on קיא עמוד ב.
kuf yud aleph amud bais. He says: דכיון דכל יומא שרי ליה,
dekeivan dechol yoma shari lei, since every day you undo it, לא
דמי מידי לקשר של קיימא. lo dami midi lekesher shel kayama. It's
completely out of that category. So there's דאורייתא d'oraisa which is forever.
There's מותר muttar which is something that's basically done and undone on
a daily basis. Since it's literally daily, is there some maybe every
few days? Whatever. But anyway, certainly on a daily basis. And then
there's things in the middle that are therefore a semi-permanent period of
time or whatever for at least not so temporary, and that's אסור
דרבנן. asur d'rabbanan. So for example, the next רש"י Rashi and yesterday
when we said about the rope that goes through the loop on
the boat or the
camel. So רש"י Rashi there says, the first wide line of רש"י
Rashi on קיב עמוד א, kuf yud bais amud aleph, the end
of the line: מפני שפעמים שמניח שם שבוע או שבועיים. mipnei shepeamim
shemaniach sham shavua o shavuayim. Sometimes you might leave it there for
a week or longer. Okay? The first רש"י Rashi קיב עמוד א,
kuf yud bais amud aleph, the first line on the top of
the page near the end of the line. Okay, so for רש"י,
Rashi, if it's just a day, it's מותר. muttar. If it's forever,
it's דאורייתא. d'oraisa. If it's for like a week or two, that's
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. What about the space between a day and a week?
Who knows. Okay, that's רש"י Rashi though. It's a question of degree
of permanence. רמב"ם Rambam says differently. רמב"ם Rambam says it's not about
permanence. It's we spoke about, you know, קשר הגמלים, kesher hagemalim, קשר
הספנים, kesher hasapanin, camel drivers and sailors. רמב"ם Rambam says that one
definition is one part of the criteria for דאורייתא d'oraisa is that
it would be a קשר אומן, kesher uman, a craftsperson, professional knot.
Exactly how you define that is unclear. Some people want to mean
that all that really means is a knot that is very tight
and that lasts. But it's not clear that the רמב"ם Rambam would
describe it that broadly. Some type of a
very professional craftsperson knot plus קיימא. kayama. But because the רמב"ם Rambam
adds the criteria of קשר אומן, kesher uman, the רמב"ם's Rambam definition
of קיימא kayama is not as long as רש"י's. Rashi The רמב"ם's
Rambam definition of קיימא kayama does not mean forever. קיימא kayama means,
no, I mean, again, he doesn't exactly quantify it, but the רמב"ם
Rambam has two criteria, so he doesn't define קיימא kayama in as
extreme terms as רש"י. Rashi. So for the רמב"ם, Rambam, what's מותר?
muttar? Is he not more מיקל? meikil?
Well, it's a combination of two. He's more מחמיר machmir because there's
a lower definition of קיימא. kayama. He's more מיקל meikil because he
adds a new criteria called professional knot. So it's not a clear
קולא kulo or חומרא. chumra. He makes one thing that makes it
harder to be a דאורייתא, d'oraisa, but he lowers the definition of
what קיימא kayama is.
In other words,
if
קיימא kayama is less than forever, it's easier to be over on
the דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But then you add a new criteria of craftsperson,
so it's harder to be over. Okay, so that's the רמב"ם. Rambam.
Now what makes it מותר muttar completely? מותר muttar completely is that
it has neither of those characteristics. It's neither professional nor is it
קיימא. kayama. So that's again like, you know, your garment, your tie,
your shoes, the types of things we're going to be talking about
today. What's דרבנן? d'rabbanan? דרבנן d'rabbanan is it has one of those
two characteristics. It's either קיימא kayama or it is professional. Okay, so
for the רמב"ם, Rambam, for example, the string through the loop of
the boat or the loop of the camel, that might be professional
and not קיימא. kayama. Or if it's קיימא kayama and not professional.
Okay, so the רמב"ם Rambam has those two criteria and either one
of them make it דרבנן. d'rabbanan. The question is קיימא kayama for
him is easier to reach than קיימא kayama for רש"י. Rashi. רש"י,
Rashi, קיימא kayama literally means permanent. Okay, let's take a look now
at the גמרא. Gemara. Four lines down, מפתח חלוקא. mafteach chaluka. Four
lines down, מפתח חלוקא. Miftach Chaluka. So one, now we're talking about
the things that are completely מותר Mutar and the first one is
the opening of the garment. You have let's say, you've got let's
say like a blouse or a shirt, you know that's got like,
like sort of like a you know laces through the top, right?
That you tighten the laces. You've seen those types of things, right?
So okay, so פשיטא Pshita obviously that should be מותר. Mutar. לא
צריכא דאית ליה תרי דשי. Lo tzricha d'is lei try dashi. It
has basically, okay רש"י Rashi also says that this might be like
a strap that goes I don't know across like crisscrosses your you
know your back or your front. Anyway, it has two of those
straps. מהו דתימא חד מינייהו בטולי מבטיל ליה, Mahu d'teima chad mineihu
betulei mevatel lei, I might think that, you know it's not obvious
that you undo each strap. Some people might undo one strap and
like squeeze out of the garment even though it's a lot easier
when you undo both straps. It's very funny, we're going to find
out today that they were just as lazy as they were at
the time of the גמרא Gemara that they by I think, I
thought I'm the only one "Oh I don't have to really untie
my shoes, just kick them off." Anyway the גמרא's Gemara going to
all be discussing about that, about you might not fully bother to
undo the straps of your garment, so maybe I would be afraid
that therefore it would be permanent. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan
that we're not concerned about that, that we assume that people, that
they are made for regular taking off even if every now and
then you might be lazy and not bother. וחוטי שבכה, V'chutei shvacha,
the straps around the hairnet. פשיטא Pshita of course, you know that
should be מותר. Mutar. No, לא צריכא דרווחא לה, Lo tzricha dirvicha
lah,
the hairnet is a little bit loose on the head. מהו דתימא
מישלף שלפא לה, Mahu d'teima mishlaf shalfa lah, she's not going to
bother to undo the straps, she'll just you know yank it off
her head. קא משמע לן דאיתתא חסה אשיערה, Ka mashma lan d'itteta
chasa a'saara, no, the woman is concerned that it'll ruin her hair
ומישרא שריא לה, U'mishra sharya lah, she'll undo the strap. So yes
it's possible and maybe we should be concerned that you'll leave it
and therefore it'll be, it's not קיימא, Kayama, more like a קיימא,
Kayama, it won't be undone on the you know the same, it
won't be undone on a daily basis. Well, we're not concerned about
that. רצועות מנעל וסנדל, Retzuot minal v'sandal,
straps of a shoe and a sandal. איתמר. Itmar. התיר רצועות מנעל
וסנדל. Heitir retzuot minal v'sandal. So what happened if you undid the
straps of a sandal of, of of a shoe or sandal? תני
חדא חייב חטאת, Tani chada chayav chatat, that's one ברייתא Braisa says
you're חייב Chayav a sin offering, so that's דאורייתא, De'oraisa, which would
also mean making the straps would be a... would be דאורייתא. De'oraisa.
ותני אידך פטור אבל
אסור, V'tani idach patur aval assur, one says you're exempt biblically but
it's rabbinically forbidden. ותני אידך מותר לכתחילה, V'tani idach mutar l'chatchila, and
a third ברייתא Braisa said that it's even permissible on the outset.
So all of this is, there's three possibilities by undoing, it's also
three possibilities by making the knots. So how are we going to
you know deal with all of this? Are they describing different scenarios?
Are they debating? So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא מנעל אמנעל קשיא
סנדל אסנדל. Kashya minal a'minal kashya sandal a'sandal. We have contradictions both
within these ברייתות Braisos of what the different rulings are and between
these ברייתות Braisos and our משנה Mishna about whether a shoe and
a sandal is מותר Mutar or is it אסור Assur or is
it חייב. Chayav. So now the גמרא's Gemara going to describe different
scenarios where all three of these play out. מנעל אמנעל לא קשיא,
Minal a'minal lo kashya, shoe on shoe is not difficult. הא דקתני
חייב חטאת, Ha d'katani chayav chatat, when do we say that it's
a sin offering to, it's biblical violation to make a strap, to
tie a strap on a shoe? באושכפי, B'ushkafei, that's talking about shoemakers.
So if they're actually taking, doing some of the straps or the
knots that stay on the shoe after they're made. They're not talking
about you the purchaser, you know who does and undoes straps after
you've bought it. We're talking about in the making of the shoe
itself that certain straps are tied on. So that's a permanent tying
on. You could also be a מכה בפטיש Makeh b'patish maybe, but
before you get to that you're actually making, you know it's actually
a permanent attachment to the shoe. That's חייב. Chayav. פטור אבל אסור,
Patur aval assur, rabbinically forbidden, בדרבנן, B'derabbanan, which means רש"י Rashi says
it means the straps that the way rabbis would wear their shoes.
It's quite fascinating. But what does this mean? Apparently that they would,
you know we're talking actually about the way you strap on, you
tie on your shoe.
And the concern is is that you might leave it that way
somewhat permanently because you might, because you might tie it a little
loosely. And if you tie it a little bit loosely, so then
you're going to kick off your shoes. If you keep, some people
are like that right? They keep their laced shoes tied for like
a long period of time and they just like put them on
and kick them off and put them on without undoing the straps.
They're not going to fall off their feet being that
loose?
You have to really squeeze them on, I'm talking out of experience,
okay. All right
anyway,
but
or maybe you kick them off and then you don't put them
on again for the next few days. So that type of a
thing is פטור אבל אסור Patur aval assur because it doesn't, according
to רש"י Rashi it seems like if it's not going to be
undone on a daily basis that already makes it אסור. Assur. So
before I mentioned that רש"י Rashi said, you know אסור Assur is
for a week and מותר Mutar is a day. Here he more
sort of emphasizes that things that are not going to be on
a daily basis it's actually going to be פטור אבל אסור. Patur
aval assur. Okay, yes but you don't really, רש"י Rashi says you
don't leave it that way permanently because there are times when you
have to actually either loosen it or maybe even tighten it, particularly
tighten it because let's say you're walking through mud and you don't
want the mud to get into the shoe, so then you will
really tighten it. But generally you leave it, on a general basis
you leave it tied but a little bit loose and therefore it
doesn't, it you know it is more than just a complete. be
temporary knot. Yes.
When does it become אסור? assur?
Yeah, so that's what I said. It's not clear. רש"י Rashi spoke
in the משנה, Mishna, if you leave it for a week it's
אסור, assur, if you leave it for a day it's מותר. muttar.
The space between those is not clear.
Right, no, but when you tie it, is it your כוונה kavana
or...
Oh, I see. Yeah, that's a good point, which is obviously you
can only be doing something wrong at the moment of tying. If
you tied it with the intention to, you know, to take it
off that day and then you decided, you know, oh, I'm going
to leave it, obviously you retrospectively didn't do something wrong. But what
if you tied it and you sort of somewhat knew without really
thinking about it that you might not undo it? Or it was
the type of knot, for example. Okay, I although I sometimes do
kick off my shoes, I'm very מחמיר machmir on מוצאי שבת motzei
Shabbos to untie my shoelaces, okay, for this reason. Right, because if
I because if I was planning on untying it and I changed
my mind, that's one thing. But if I sort of am semi-aware
that I don't always undo it and I'm tying it anyway and
I'm not undoing it, right, so then that could be a problem
because that's sort of my awareness of the type of knot I'm
doing. For example, if you really emphasize the one day,
there are people that are מחמיר machmir and maybe rightfully so that
if they get the גלילה gelila on שבת מנחה Shabbos mincha they
don't make a bow knot on the, you know, for with the
גארטל gartel around the ספר תורה Sefer Torah because the next time
you're going to undo it is going to be Monday. It's going
to be more than a day, and you're aware of that. Does
Velcro help? Velcro helps, yeah.
It's not a professional knot though, is it?
What? רש"י, Rashi, it's not about professional. רש"י, Rashi, it's all about
degree of permanence. Now does a... no, רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi has...
רש"י Rashi says: forever is דאורייתא, d'oraissa, for a day is מותר,
muttar, for a week and and more permanent than that is דרבנן.
d'rabonon. What about the space between a week and a day? Not
so clear. So it's a degree of permanence. So here, who needs
professional? It's not about professional for רש"י. Rashi. Okay, fine. But I'm
saying, but we tend to be מחמיר machmir for רש"י. Rashi. We're
מחמיר machmir sort of both ways. Anyway, okay. So that's so that's
what that is. But yes, that's a very good question. You know,
it doesn't retrospectively become that way, but what your general way of
what the general reality of this knot/fact factor is in. You know,
in the end
we should also be with those of us who kick off our
shoes, we should also be מחמיר machmir to untie מוצאי שבת motzei
Shabbos or is it...
I would say so, if you generally kick off your shoes and
you don't undo the knot and you leave it that way until,
you know, I don't know. I mean, now if you undo it
the next morning, it's fine. But if you're not going to wear
if they're your שבת Shabbos shoes, you're not going to wear them
until the next שבת, Shabbos, I would definitely say you have to
get in the practice of untying your shoes מוצאי שבת. motzei Shabbos.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says that's exactly this like דרבנן
d'rabonon case, that would be... we shouldn't do a full
knot then though, is that what you're saying, for גלילה gelila on
ספר תורה? Sefer Torah?
Yeah, I mean the question also is how much for רש"י Rashi
the issue of a bow would be a different category. We'll see
about that tomorrow. Okay, so let's take a look, the גמרא Gemara
says... okay. מותר לכתחילה, muttar l'chatchila, totally מותר, muttar, בבני מחוזא. b'vnei
Mechuza.
Those are the people of מחוזא. Mechuza. מחוזא Mechuza was a very
cosmopolitan town and basically רש"י Rashi says they were very careful they
were very concerned about their, you know, appearances, so they would not
keep their shoes tied loosely, they would tie them very tightly. Be
very important about their appearances, and if they're tied very tightly you're
going to have to undo it that night and therefore it's not
a problem. They're metrosexual. All right, okay, moving on. סנדל אסנדל לא
קשיא. sandal asandal lo kashya. Now how about the sandal? Those are
shoes. How about sandals? Sandals are a little bit different because the
sandal, the straps are actually, you know, part of the whole, you
know, like part of the whole of the whole like construction of
the shoe. So, חדא קתני חייב חטאת. hada katani chayav chattas. When
do we say חייב חטאת? chayav chattas?
Similar like we said before about the shoe. בדטייעי דקטרי אושכפי. b'd'toi
d'katri ushkhafi.
Like the sandals used by טייעי toi which are like the Arab
nomads or merchants, you know, whatever the the travelers, that they that
the shoemakers would tie for them. So meaning it's basically these are
people that are keeping their sandals that don't undo the straps and
they keep the straps on permanently. I mean they obviously take their
shoes off, but they don't actually undo the point of where the
straps connect to the actual base of the shoe. And therefore, and
it's done by the shoemaker, so you get the אומן umman here
for the רמב"ם, Rambam, and therefore it's biblical. פטור אבל אסור, patur
aval assur, rabbinically forbidden. בחומרא דקטרי אינהו. b'chumrsa d'katri inhu. So this
is the sandals of other people that are how do they translate
בחומרא b'chumrsa by the way? Do you have a translation there? No,
okay.
Anyone know?
Amateurs. They say amateurs? All right, that's interesting. Okay, anyway they or
ordinary people, that's חומרא chumrsa anyway. All right, I wasn't so clear
in רש"י Rashi either. Anyway, fine. So it means that it means
that your layperson קטרי אינהו, katri inhu, the laypeople, you know, you
know, you know do and therefore it is and therefore you do
your own straps, so maybe you do put your strap back onto
the sandal base itself but you do it yourself and... And A,
so A it's not אומן, umman, and B, it is not what
you call it, and B, it's apparently not permanent. You will undo
it, you will undo it every every few days. So that's where
it's דרבנן. derabbanan. מותר לכתחילה mutar l'chatchila
what? Apparently you could construct, you know, totally remove the strap from
the sandal and put it back on. That was something a layperson
could do. And apparently a layperson would do, so not just undo
it from your leg but actually it seems like that's what we're
talking about.
Okay, where were we? Okay, so רש"י Rashi says in sometimes it
would last a week or a month, so רש"י Rashi is back
to the idea of a week.
So that's דרבנן. derabbanan. Where were we? קצינהו. katzyeinuhu. מותר לכתחילה בסנדל
דנפקי ביה בי תרי. mutar lechatchila besandal denafki beih bi harei. So
what's מותר לכתחילה? mutar l'chatchila? A sandal that is shared by two
people. So if it's shared by two people, not at the same
time, but anyway then regularly you will have to undo the straps
and readjust them for the other person, okay? So we're not again
talking about the straps of like just tying it on your leg,
we're talking about some type of a knot that's keeping it attached
to the base, okay, but that actually that was could be adjusted
by the layperson, and if you share your sandal with somebody else,
you're going to be undoing it on a regular basis, so
that's not a problem then, right?
Right,
exactly. כי דרב יהודה. ki-de-Rav Yehudah. This is like רב יהודה. Rav
Yehudah. דרב יהודה אמר
אחוה דרב סלא חסידא. de-Rav Yehudah amar achvei de-Rav Salla Chasida. רב
יהודה Rav Yehudah the brother of רב סלא חסידא Rav Salla Chasida
הוה ליה ההוא זוגא דסנדלי. hava lei hahu zuga de-sandalei. He had
a pair of sandals. זימנין נפיק ביה איהו. zimnin nafik beih ihu.
Sometimes he went out with it. זימנין נפיק ביה ינוקיה. zimnin nafik
beih yanukeih. אתא לקמיה דאביי. ata le-kamei de-Abaye. He went to אביי.
Abaye. אמר ליה כי האי גוונא מאי. amar lei ki-hai gavna mai.
What's the story about these on שבת? Shabbat? אמר ליה חייב חטאת.
amar lei chayav chatat.
Oh boy. So he says you're a biblical transgression. אמר ליה השתא
פטור ואסור קא קשיא לי. amar lei hashta patur ve-assur ka kashya
li. Here I came to you, I didn't even understand why it
would be rabbinically forbidden. חייב חטאת קאמרת לי? chayav chatat ka-amrat li?
You're telling me חייב חטאת? chayav chatat? So מאי טעמא? mai taama?
So then אביי Abaye said back to him,
so why do you think it should be מותר? mutar? So אמר
ליה משום דבכל יומא זימנין נפקינא ביה אנא זימנין נפיק ביה ינוקא.
amar lei mishum de-vchol yoma zimnin nafkina beih ana zimnin nafik beih
yanuka. Because that sometimes on a regular basis, even on a weekday,
sometimes I'll wear it, sometimes my kid will wear it, and therefore
we will regularly undo the knots and change them on a regular
basis. So אמר ליה אי הכי מותר לכתחילה. amar lei i hachi
mutar lechatchila. Oh okay, then it's מותר. mutar. So we went from
חייב chayav to saying it's מותר. mutar. So רש"י Rashi says why
did he think it's חייב? chayav? Because he thought that it was
A, not with a kid, it was permanent. What about the point
that we said before that even that would just be פטור patur
if you're not actually because even a normal person undoes it every
now and then? So רש"י Rashi says he thought maybe that he
was even talking about that it was that it was like a
shoemaker's type of a knot. It's not exactly clear why he thought
it was חייב. chayav. Anyway, but it is actually מותר mutar if
it's undone. So the basic principle is clear according to רש"י. Rashi.
If it's there for like a week or more it's דרבנן. derabbanan.
If it's permanent it's דאורייתא. de-oraisa. If it's a day it's מותר.
mutar. The space between a day and a week is not so
clear. And according to the רמב"ם, Rambam, the other factor in all
of these would be that the thing that the דאורייתא de-oraisa scenario
was when the shoemaker did it, so then it became a מעשה
אומן, maaseh umman, it became a craftperson's knot. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara continues.
So if you're the type of person that always undoes your shoes,
always, and then you never have a problem.
Right, again, part of the question with all of this gets to
the issue about how much is it about כוונה, kavannah, how much
is it about the nature of the knot, but yes, that is
definitely a factor.
Okay, רב ירמיה הוה קאזיל בתריה דרבי אבהו בכרמלית. Rav Yirmiyah hava
ka-azil batrei de-Rabbi Abbahu be-charmelit. רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah was walking behind
רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu in a כרמלית. charmelit. איפסיק רצועה דסנדליה. ipsik
retzuah de-sandaleih. So the strap of his sandal got undone. And remember
that making tying the strap of your sandal is at least a
דרבנן derabbanan unless it's a very special case. So אמר ליה מאי
נעביד לה. amar lei mai naavid lah. So he said to him,
what can we do with it? What, you know, I don't want
to leave my sandal here, but I can't redo the knot, so
and why can't I carry it? Because it's a כרמלית, charmelit, it's
אסור דרבנן assur derabbanan to carry it. So what am I going
to do? I can't get it so I can wear it again,
I can't carry it, what am I supposed to do? So אמר
ליה שקול גמי לח דחזי למאכל בהמה. amar lei shkul gmi lach
de-chazi le-maachal behemah. Go find a like a moist type of a
reed or something that is that can be eaten by animals and
therefore it's not מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay, don't pluck it out of the
ground, find one that's
already, you know, available, that so therefore it's not מוקצה, muktzeh, it's
not permanent because nobody's going to leave this type of a whatever,
like a vine let's say, you know, a piece of a vine,
and you know, מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbat you're going to take it
off and replace it with something so completely not permanent. It's completely
temporary and then you're okay. Now, what's to say that within four
אמות amos of where he was standing he could find something like
this? I don't know, but he said שקול, shkul, he didn't say
look for one, he said שקול, shkul, so presumably there was one
right there that was available that he said here, take that. What?
Doesn't it, isn't it אסור assur to carry that?
No, within four אמות amos you can carry even לכתחילה, lechatchila, yeah.
Right, right, right. You have a question, Ari?
No, I was just going to say they go to there and
then.
Yeah, but he said שקול, shkul, take it, so presumably it was
like right there. Okay, so okay, of. אביי, Abaye, now that was
where רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya told אביי. Abaye. Now we have a
story with אביי, Abaye, הוי קאי קמיה דרב יוסף. hava kai kamei
d'Rav Yosef. I'm sorry, that was not רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiya, that
was what רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu told רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmiya. Now
אביי Abaye was in front of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אתפסקיה רצועה,
itpaskei ritzua, so אביי's Abaye sandal strap broke. Now רש״י Rashi says
that this is in a חצר, chatzer, in a courtyard so there's
not a carrying problem. Okay, but there's a new problem: does the
sandal become מוקצה muktzeh when the strap breaks? Okay. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, מאי עביד ליה? mai avid lei? He said, what can
I do? אמר ליה, amar lei, שבקיה, shevukia, leave it. Leave it,
it's in a חצר, chatzer, nobody's going to take it, it's in
your backyard, we'll pick it up after שבת. Shabbos. Okay. So מאי
שנא מדרבי ירמיה? mai shna mid'Rabbi Yirmiya? Why is it different than
רבי ירמיה? Rabbi Yirmiya? Why don't you give me some solution like
you gave him? In anyway, in the רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya case,
the only problem was a carrying one, it wasn't a מוקצה muktzeh
problem. So if you're telling me to leave it and we're in
a חצר, chatzer, then you must think it's מוקצה. muktzeh. Why is
this more מוקצה muktzeh than רבי ירמיה's Rabbi Yirmiya case? התם לא
מינטר הכא מינטר. hasam lo mintar, hacha mintar. Well,
first of all, there it was out in the open, it wasn't
protected. Here it's protected so we don't have to find a leniency.
So he said, but who cares? אמנא הוא? amana hu? It's still
a vessel, it's still a כלי, kli, shouldn't be מוקצה. muktzeh. I
don't care that it's possible that, oh, it'll be protected, I want
to bring it inside. ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'is eima, and now what makes
it, what makes it usable? Here's what makes it usable: דאיבעית אימא
הפיכנא לה מימינא לשמאלא. d'iba'is eima hafichna lah miyamina l'smola. I can
reverse it from the right to the left. What does this mean?
רש״י Rashi says that you had two straps, you had a strap
on the instep on the inside and a strap on the outer
step. If you were to fix the outer strap, it would look
very visible and it would look, you know, it wouldn't look כבודיק,
kavodig, so people if they have to fix that strap, presumably would
get a new sandal. But if you had to fix the inner
strap, okay, then nobody really sees it so you would continue to
use it. So he says, so apparently this was a case, this
is the way רש״י Rashi goes, that the outer strap broke. So
the answer was, oh, it's completely מוקצה, muktzeh, it's no longer usable
because nobody's going to bother fixing the outer strap, so whatever, it's
garbage. And he said, what do you mean? If I can switch
it from the right to the left, right? If you imagine they
weren't made like our shoes, very, you know, conforming to the shape
of the foot, they were a relatively flat base. So if you
switch it from the right to the left, what was the outer
strap now becomes the inner strap, so it's still usable. And therefore
it can still be considered maybe not usable now with the broken
strap, but I can salvage it and therefore it should still be
considered a vessel and not מוקצה. muktzeh. By the way, it's very
interesting that in our entire discussion today from here on, we're going
to be talking about this issue about sandals with straps breaking right
and left, and we don't discuss another major discussion about מוקצה, muktzeh,
which is about שברי כלים, shivrei keilim, which is actually a whole
major issue in the משניות Mishnayos and גמרא. Gemara. We're going to
get to it, that something that was usable when שבת Shabbos began,
now it broke, okay, and does it remain, maybe it should be
not מוקצה muktzeh because it wasn't מוקצה muktzeh when שבת Shabbos started.
Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is going to focus only on the
specific status of a sandal with a broken strap. Yes, and not
a more general discussion, yes.
Is there not an issue of משום mishum if you're going to
leave it there? Let's say you started in your house and you
take it out, it breaks, you leave it there, you've transferred something
from a public domain to a private?
No, wearing it you didn't transfer, it's not considered transferring.
But then when you take it off, you leave it there.
It fell off, the strap was, anyway, leaving it was, as in
you can leave something. I can walk into the middle of the
street, take off my jacket, leave it there and leave. I haven't
transferred, I wore it. Okay, the same way putting it back on
isn't now carrying it back into the house, it's wearing it.
Alright, so let's take a look.
So he says, אמנא הוא? amana hu? It's a כלי. kli. דאיבעית
אימא הפיכנא לה מימינא לשמאלא. d'iba'is eima hafichna lah miyamina l'smola. I
can switch it from the right to the left and therefore still
salvage it. אמר ליה, amar lei, מדקא מתיר רבי יוחנן אליבא דרבי
יהודה, mideka matir Rabbi Yochanan aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda, no, because we're about
to see that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in a minute will explain
something according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, not a רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda we've seen before, שמע מינה הלכה כרבי יהודה, shma mina halacha
k'Rabbi Yehuda, and therefore we see that the ruling is like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and it doesn't count as a sandal. Okay, so
what's all that about? So basically, let's now look at some other
discussion about a sandal with a broken strap and I'll prove to
you that once a strap breaks, at least an outer strap, it's
no longer a sandal. Even though you could reverse it. Let's take
a look, okay, so מאי היא? mai hi? Where, what is this
about? דתניא, detanya, סנדל שנפסקו שתי אזניו או
שתי תרסיותיו. sandal shenipsaku shtei oznatav o shtei tartsiyotav. If you have
a sandal that both of its ears broke, apparently רש״י Rashi says
these were like flaps, right, in the back that you would use
to pull it on, or both of its תרסיותיו, tartsiyotav, which are
basically the places where the straps would connect, one on the outside,
one on the inside. So if basically both of the straps or
both of the flaps broke, או שנטלה כל הכף שלו, o shenitlah
kol hakaf shelo, or the entire base was removed, so טהור, tahor,
then it's טהור. tahor. If it was טמא, tamei, right, it stops
being a vessel. When a vessel completely breaks and loses its status
as a vessel, the טומאה tumah goes off, so it becomes טהור.
tahor. אחת מאזניו או אחת מתרסיותיו, achas me'oznav o achas mitartsiyotav, if
it's only one of the flaps or one of the strap holders,
you know, one of the strap sort of inserts, which is basically,
means one of the straps, או שנטלה רוב הכף שלו, o shenitlah
rov hakaf shelo, or only the majority of the base, but the
majority... but a minority... majority is still there, טמא, tamei, it's still
טמא. tamei. You wonder how you can use a sandal with only
the minority, but maybe if it's the heel or the front, you
can walk with only putting your weight on the heel. Yeah, so
there's ways of managing. Okay, so then it remains טמא. tamei. It
remains a vessel. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer ניפסקה nifska פנימית
pnimis טמא. tamei. No, if the inner strap broke, then it is
טמא tamei because then it's
still a vessel, you will fix the inner strap. החיצונה, Hachitzona, if
the outer strap broke, טהור, tahor,
then it's even if it's only one strap it's טהור tahor because
you're not going to fix it. Okay, so here you have the
debate. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the outer strap is—the—at—once it breaks
the outer strap it's a problem, and the rabbi—not problem, loses its
status, and the rabbis say that no, even if the outer strap
breaks it's okay, you could maybe reverse it, and only if both
straps break it's a problem. So here, if it breaks it becomes
טהור, tahor, but for us, if it breaks, if it loses its
vessel status, it becomes מוקצה. muktzah. Now which way do we rule?
Does the breaking of the outer strap, is that enough to make
it lose its status? ואמר עולא ואיתימא רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן. Ve'amar Ula ve'isima Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan.
So עולא Ula said in the name of רבה בר בר חנה
Rabba bar bar Chana in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
So here's the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan we referred to before. כמחלוקת
לעניין טומאה כך מחלוקת לעניין שבת. Kemachlokes le'inyan tumah kach machlokes le'inyan
Shabbos. The same way they debate when it loses its status as
a vessel for טומאה tumah would be the same debate by שבת,
Shabbos, when does it become מוקצה, muktzah, when does it stop being
a shoe? אבל לא לעניין חליצה. Aval lo le'inyan chalitzah. But when
it comes to חליצה, chalitzah, then—then they don't debate. They don't debate
which way; everybody agrees it is a shoe or it isn't a
shoe if it loses one strap. So let's take a look. ואבינן
בה. Ve'avinan bah. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask. רבי יוחנן אליבא דמאן? Rabbi Yochanan aliba deman? According to whom
is he talking about about this חליצה chalitzah thing? Who is he
emphasizing? Which position? אילימא אליבא דרבנן, Eilima aliba derabbanan, he's talking about
from the—from the perspective of the rabbis. So he says like this.
מידי לעניין טומאה מנא הוא. Midi le'inyan tumah mana hu. The rabbis
say that it's
a vessel with one
strap,
even
the outer strap broke, for טומאה.
tumah.
So
לעניין שבת
נמי מנא הוא. Le'inyan Shabbos nami mana hu. For שבת Shabbos also,
even as
long as there's one
strap, even if the outer strap is broken, it remains a vessel.
אבל, Aval, that's what they say by טומאה tumah and שבת, Shabbos,
that either strap that breaks, as long as there's one strap, it's
still a vessel. אבל לא לחליצה. Aval lo lachalitzah. Not לחליצה. lachalitzah.
דלאו מנא הוא. Delav mana hu. There it wouldn't be a vessel.
Why not? והיכי דמי? Veheichi dami? How could that be? How could
it be that by חליצה chalitzah they would say it—it would be
different? והתנן, Vehasnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, חלצה של שמאל
בימין חליצתה כשירה. Chaltzah shel smol biyamin chalitzasa kesherah. That if you
use the left shoe on the—on the right foot—חליצה chalitzah is done
on the right foot—it's כשרה. kesherah. So for חליצה, chalitzah, even something
that could just be used for the left is okay. So why
should they more say it's not a vessel by חליצה? chalitzah? Now
it's funny, from our perspective, if anybody's ever been involved in חליצה,
chalitzah, you know they have such a huge contraption of a shoe
to make sure they're doing some exact halachic definition of a shoe.
Okay, but from the גמרא's Gemara's perspective, from the גמרא's Gemara's perspective,
it seems that חליצה chalitzah should be easier to be defined as
a vessel than it is for שבת Shabbos and טומאה. tumah. Since
you could use a left shoe on a right foot, so if
missing a strap is enough of a—it's still a vessel for טומאה
tumah and שבת, Shabbos, you certainly still be a vessel for חליצה.
chalitzah. So it wouldn't make sense why we would say the rabbis
would—would switch their position there. אלא אליבא דרבי יהודה. Ela aliba deRabbi
Yehuda. So he's talking from רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's perspective. מידי לעניין
טומאה לאו מנא הוא. Midi le'inyan tumah lav mana hu. First of
all, it's—when it loses an outer strap, it's—the outer one specifically—it's not
a vessel for טומאה. tumah. לעניין שבת נמי לאו מנא הוא. Le'inyan
Shabbos nami lav mana hu. For שבת Shabbos also, it's not a
vessel because it's מוקצה. muktzah. אבל לא לחליצה. Aval lo lachalitzah. By
חליצה chalitzah that's different. חליצה chalitzah he would agree to the rabbis
it would be a—it would be a shoe. Why? דמנא הוא. Demana
hu. It would be a shoe. Why? So because you could use
the right for the left. So that's a way of reading it,
right? That he's saying that I would actually agree there that it
would be okay even though by other things not. So no, that
doesn't make sense either. אימור דאמרינן Eimur de'amrinan חלצה של שמאל בימין
חליצתה כשירה. chaltzah shel smol biyamin chalitzasa kesherah. This is what the
גמרא Gemara is saying: when would we say that if you used
your left shoe on your right foot it would be good? היכא
דלמילתיה מנא הוא. Heicha delemilsiah mana hu. That's when it still—for its
own purpose—it's—it's a full vessel, it really is a full right shoe.
הכא דלמילתיה לאו מנא הוא. Hacha delemilsiah lav mana hu.
Here for the right shoe or for the right foot it's not
usable at all because it's the outer strap that's broken. דאמר רבי
יהודה ניפסקה החיצונה טהור. De'amar Rabbi Yehuda nifska hachitzona tahor. Because רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda normally would say that it would not be considered
a shoe. אמר לאו מנא הוא. Amar lav mana hu. It's not
a shoe. So basically the גמרא's Gemara's got this problem. What's the
problem? It says like this. It says:
for
the rabbis who say when the outer strap is broken it—it is
a shoe, we don't understand why they would change their vote by
חליצה chalitzah because presumably the—presumably the—the criteria are lower by חליצה. chalitzah.
But even for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says it's not a
shoe, okay, by שבת Shabbos and by—and by טומאה, tumah,
even though the—the criteria is lower by חליצה, chalitzah, we—it's hard to
understand of why would you call it a shoe for חליצה chalitzah
since it is not a shoe in all other areas. That should
be—that should be, you know, that's, you know, sort of
central enough that if it's never in other things considered a shoe,
to say it can't be a shoe for חליצה chalitzah either. So
we don't understand why this—you know, why one side should switch their
vote. So the גמרא Gemara says, all right, you're right, nobody switches
their vote. לעולם Le'olam לעולם אליבא דרבי יהודה אימא, Le'olam aliba d'Rabbi
Yehuda eima, he's saying according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. ואימא, Ve'eima,
don't say וחליצה v'halitza is different, say וכן לחליצה, ve'chein l'halitza, which
is a pretty radical change. So it's not saying okay, שבת Shabbos
and טומאה tumah they disagree, but they agree by חליצה. halitza. No,
no, no, they also disagree by חליצה. halitza. הא קמשמע לן, Ha
kamashma lan, so what are you telling me? The exactly this point.
דכי אמרינן חלצה של שמאל בימין חליצה כשרה, D'ki amrinan chaltzah shel
smol b'yamin halitza keshera, when do we say that if you use
a left shoe on the right foot it's good? היכא דלמילתיה מנא
הוא. Heicha d'lemiltei mana hu.
That's only when it really for its own purposes is a vessel,
when it really is a full right left shoe. אבל הכא דלמילתיה
לאו מנא הוא, Aval hacha d'lemiltei lav mana hu, here where for
its purpose it's not a vessel, it doesn't work for חליצה halitza
either. Okay, so basically just to repeat: if it broke the outer
strap, okay, if it broke the inner strap everybody says it's still
a vessel because you would fix it. If it broke the outer
strap, you normally wouldn't fix it, but you might be able to
reverse it to the other to the other foot. So what's the
story? Does it lose its status or not? The Rabbis say it
loses its status as a shoe, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it
does not. Okay, and then רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan makes a statement
that whatever the debate is, they agree by חליצה. halitza. But the
גמרא Gemara resists that interpretation. Okay, because it would not make any
sense to say the Rabbis would say it would be no good
by חליצה, halitza, because חליצה halitza has lower standards. It wouldn't make
any sense to say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it would be
good for חליצה, halitza, because if it's not a shoe for its
own use, you know, for its own foot in general purposes, it
won't be a shoe for חליצה. halitza. So basically we we have
him say that it's the same story by חליצה, halitza, but again
the emphasis being that he's explaining רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The same
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that said it's not a shoe by שבת
Shabbos and מוקצה muktzah would also say it's not a shoe by
חליצה. halitza. And even though we have this idea right foot, left
foot, you could use the other shoe, that doesn't make a difference.
If it's not a shoe by שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom
Tov, it's not a shoe by חליצה. halitza. What's the אפשט apshat
of all this? He's bothering to explain the position of רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So since he's bothering to explain the position of רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we infer that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan rules like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. And says that when it's missing the outer
strap, it stops being a shoe. Okay, and that's going back to
the case why he didn't let him carry the shoe with the
broken outer strap in the courtyard, because it's מוקצה, muktzah, it stops
being a shoe. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? Umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Did רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say that, that we rule like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and when it breaks the outer strap it stops being
a shoe?
והאמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה, Ve'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'stam Mishna,
we generally we rule like a סתם משנה. stam Mishna. ותנן, U'tenan,
and here's what we taught in the משנה Mishna in כלים. Keilim.
סנדל שנפסקה אחת מאזניו, Sandal she'nifseka achas m'oznav, if a sandal, one
of the flaps breaks, or one of the, or one of the
ותיקנה v'tiknah and you fixed it, טמא מדרס, tamei midras, it is
טמא מדרס. tamei midras. So, and the גמרא Gemara is assuming that
the question of the flaps is the same as the strap. Now,
you know what, I won't read the parentheses for a minute, we'll
get to that later. So if one of them breaks it is
טמא. tamei. So if one of them breaks it's טמא, tamei, presumably
one of the flaps, one of the straps breaks it's טמא. tamei.
That means presumably even the outer strap. So מאי לאו לא שנא
פנימית ולא שנא חיצונית? Mai lav lo shena penimis v'lo shena chitzonis?
Doesn't matter inner, doesn't matter outer, and and therefore you see that
even if an outer strap breaks, it still is a vessel. So
the גמרא Gemara says: לא, פנימית דוקא. Lo, penimis davka. No, we're
only talking about if the inner one broke. You should have said
that! אבל חיצונית מאי? Aval chitzonis mai? So what are you going
to say? You're going to say if the outer one broke טהור,
tahor, it's טהור tahor and consistent with the position of רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? אי הכי, Ei hachi, if that's true, אדקא תני נפסקה
שניה ותיקנה טהור מן המדרס אבל טמא מגע מדרס, ad'ka tani nifseka
shniya v'tiknah tahor min hamidras aval tamei maga midras, it's about to
say that if the second one broke, it becomes טהור. tahor. I'll
unpack that statement in a minute, but let me finish the train
of thought. If it says, and that was the one that was
taken out above, it goes on to say that if the second
strap broke it becomes טהור. tahor. Why do you have to say
that? נפלוג בדידי. Niflog b'didi. Why don't you make the distinction within
the case of one strap itself? במה דברים אמורים שנפסקה פנימית, Bamei
devarim amurim she'nifseka penimis,
when is it true that if one strap breaks it remains טמא?
tamei? if it's the inner strap. אבל חיצונית, Aval chitzonis, the outer
strap טהור, tahor, it would it would be טהור. tahor. Right? If
you say if both break it's טהור, tahor, well actually that's not
true. You don't need, I mean, it's not you don't need both
to break. Both break is the inner and the outer, but really
all you need to break is the outer strap for it to
be טהור. tahor. Okay, so if it's so here we got a
problem. This משנה Mishna says that if one strap broke it's טמא,
tamei, two straps טהור. tahor. So how does that fit with the
position that whenever the outer strap breaks it becomes טהור? tahor? And
you can't say that that's what it means, because then it would
have said that. It would have said if the inner strap broke
it's טמא, tamei, the outer strap it's טהור. tahor. So we got
a problem. This one says the outer strap is still a shoe
and that's not consistent with what we said before, that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan rules like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So אמר רב יצחק
בן יוסף, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef, תהא משנתנו בסנדל שיש לו
ארבע אזנים וארבע תסיותיהן. Tehei mishnasenu b'sandal she'yesh lo arba oznayim v'arba
tasiyoseihen. שלא כדברי רבי יהודה, She'lo k'divrei Rabbi Yehuda, שרבי יוחנן... she'Rabbi
Yochanan... Okay. Say
our
say this משנה Mishna is talking when it talks about one strap
and two straps, it's talking that you have four straps, you have
two and four flaps, two on the outside and two on the
inside, not one on each. Okay, so in that scenario, right, if
one strap broke, meaning... one of the outer straps breaks, it is
טמא. tamei. If both of these straps, meaning both of the outer
straps break, then it is טהור, tahor, but it is actually talking
about a very special case of a four strap sandal, and the
גמרא Gemara recognizes that that's a very weak resolution, which is why
it ends by, so at least, you know, I realize that this
is really weak, but at least then it won't make רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan contradict himself. Now, I have to tell you two a
couple things. Let me step back first of all and explain that
was a little complicated, which I'm sure it was. First of all,
it's very funny that the גמרא Gemara creates this as a מחלוקת
Machlokes of רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan never explicitly
ruled like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. All he said was since he
was explaining רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, and even that, it wasn't clear,
it was only the way the גמרא Gemara interpreted what he said,
you know, that he's explaining רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, that means he
rules like רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, that the outer strap makes it
lose its identity. He also never said we explicitly rule like this
סתם משנה. stam mishna. But the גמרא Gemara does that a lot.
It says since רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan makes this global statement we
rule like a סתם משנה, stam mishna, we can assume he means
that 100 percent of the time and ask that that סתם משנה
stam mishna doesn't agree with another statement that he's made. So that
gives the גמרא Gemara its problem that here רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
we interpret him saying that the outer strap break it's טהור. tahor.
Here's a סתם משנה stam mishna that seems to say that even
if the outer strap break it's טמא. tamei. And we have a
very weak resolution. The resolution is, is that it was a special
case where there were two straps on the outside and therefore it's
still טמא. tamei. But if there's the normal case of only one
strap, then he would say that it is טהור tahor and recognize
that it's a very weak resolution and that's why it says שלא
לשבור דבריו של רבי יוחנן. shelo lishbor devarav sheRebbi Yochanan. Now I
do want to explain something, you know, it's probably too complicated already,
but I do want to explain something about this line I ran
over because it's an interesting concept. So let's read the line again
where it said, you know, you could just read it above where
it was taken out but that's the line I'm going to be
unpacking, so it's clearer there with the parentheses and the stars. So
one strap breaks, it is טמא, tamei, it's still a shoe. Okay,
even though you afterwards fixed the strap. Okay, because it, well not
even though. Okay, so it broke, whether you fixed it or not
it remains a shoe. נפסקה שנייה ותיקנה טהור מלקמי מדרס אבל טמא
מגע מדרס. nipsika hashniya vetikna tahor mi-lekamay medras aval tamei maga medras.
The second one breaks, it stops being a shoe, so it stops
being מדרס, medras, but it
still is טהור מגע מדרס. tahor maga medras. Touch in מדרס. medras.
What does that mean? טמא מגע מדרס. tamei maga medras. What does
this mean? It means a זב zav is wearing a shoe. So
because he supports his weight on the shoe, the shoe is מדרס,
medras, it's an אב הטומאה, av hatuma, okay, it's supporting that's a
thing, you sit on something, stand on something, it's an אב הטומאה.
av hatuma. It's a מדרס. medras. This shoe, one strap breaks, it's
still a shoe, it's still טמא מדרס, tamei medras, it's an אב
הטומאה. av hatuma. The second strap breaks, it stops being a shoe.
Okay, so the מדרס medras טומאה tuma goes away. But, and this
is a very bizarre idea, something
that was an אב הטומאה מדרס, av hatuma medras, even though now
it's no longer an אב הטומאה, av hatuma, it was in a
way touching itself. So it remains טמא tamei as מגע מדרס, maga
medras, something that touched a מדרס. medras. Now how would it if
it stops being a shoe, how does it remain טמא? tamei? So
רש"י Rashi has two versions. One version רש"י Rashi says is it
stops being a shoe, but it still can be used as something
else. I don't know, it could be used as a backscratcher. So
it can't be a מדרס medras because now it's a backscratcher. Okay,
because the straps broke, it's no longer a shoe, but it's still
a backscratcher. So it can't be a מדרס, medras, but when it
switched from being a shoe to a backscratcher, so it was in
a way touching itself and it becomes something that touched a מדרס.
medras. Okay, and that's a very bizarre idea, but we have that
in a couple of places. תוספות Tosfos discusses is that really what's
happening? He's bothered by that idea, the idea that it touched itself.
Okay, that's the first point though, it's טמא מגע מדרס. tamei maga
medras. Now the other thing though that רש"י Rashi says and this
will come up here, we don't even mean that it became a
non-shoe. If you notice this case was described that a strap broke
and you fixed it. The other strap broke and you fixed it.
So it does remain a shoe. But it's a different shoe. It's
a different shoe because both of the straps have been replaced. If
both of the straps have been taken away, it would have stopped
being a shoe. This never stopped being a shoe because every time
a strap broke it was immediately fixed. But since by the end
of the day both straps has been changed, it now has an
identity as a different shoe. So it doesn't have the old טומאה
tuma of מדרס. medras. If a זב zav would put his foot
in it again, it would be מדרס. medras. But it stopped being
the old shoe, but again it was a new shoe that touched
the old shoe so it's מגע מדרס. maga medras. So there's two
ideas here. One is when it changes its identity the טומאה tuma
doesn't go off completely, it's still this idea of touching itself, מגע
מדרס, maga medras, so it's not an אב av it's a ראשון.
rishon. And the second point is that when both straps are replaced
even though it never stopped being a shoe, it now becomes a
new shoe. And that's the idea that the גמרא Gemara says happened.
Basically, it comes from being, it becomes a new shoe essentially. What?
Let's say he brings, like,
not because it's being a new shoe, because both, because had those
straps not been replaced, it would not have been a shoe at
all. Well let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara is going to
continue with this point. Okay. So, אמר רב, amar Rav, said רב,
Rav, הלכה כרבי יהודה. halakha keRebbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה.
Rebbi Yehuda. I'm sorry, I skipped a line. כי אתא רבין אמר
רבי יוחנן אמר רב חנינא בר אבא אמר רב הלכה כרבי יהודה.
ki ata Ravin amar Rebbi Yochanan amar Rav hanina bar Abba amar
Rav halakha keRebbi Yehuda. רבי יוחנן אמר. Rebbi Yochanan amar. Oh, we
have a better resolution. We tried to say that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan ruled like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because he explained the position
of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. You know, when רבין Ravin came from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he said רב Rav ruled like רבי יהודה;
Rabbi Yehuda; רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan does not rule like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So that solves all problem. According to רבין, Ravin, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and if
the outer strap breaks, it really, if the outer strap breaks, it
still is טמא, tamei, it's still a shoe, which also means it's
not מוקצה muktzah and means you can carry it. Okay. ומי אמר
רבי יוחנן הכי? Umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Did רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan say that? We don't want to give up what we said
before. והא מימטרץ רבי יוחנן אליבא דרבי יהודה? Ve'ha mimatretz Rabbi Yochanan
aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda? We just got through saying that since רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan explained רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position, שמע מינה כרבי יהודה
סבירא ליה, shema mina k'Rabbi Yehuda svira lei, he rules like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So that's אמוראי נינהו ואליבא דרבי יהודה. Amorai ninhu
ve'aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda. Rather than saying we were wrong, that although he's
explaining רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he doesn't rule that way, we're saying
okay, there's a debate of the אמוראים Amoraim of what the tradition
was of how רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ruled. So at the end
of the day, we have this debate of if the outer strap
breaks, does it remain a shoe or not? Debated between רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and the rabbis and perhaps two different versions of what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. Now we're going to get back to
this fascinating idea of replacing both of the straps in another case.
Okay. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. This is a little bit easier and
I think a lot more sort of philosophically interesting. כל כלי בעלי
בתים. Kol klei ba'alei batim. We have said in another context that
any normal vessel of a homeowner, meaning your average type of vessel,
not a professional one, שיעורן כרמונים. shiuran k'rimonim. It only loses its
status as a vessel for טומאה tuma if it has a hole
the size of a pomegranate, because any smaller size hole you'll just
use it for like oranges, pomegranates and so on. Only when it's
got a big hole is it unusable and not a vessel. Now,
בעי חזקיה. Ba'ei Chizkiyah. So חזקיה Chizkiyah raised the following question. ניקב
כמוציא זית. Nikav kemotzi zayit. Let's say it just had a hole
the size of an olive. It didn't lose its status. וסתמו. Usetamo.
And then you filled up that hole, you put putty on it
or whatever, you filled it up. וחזר וניקב כמוציא זית. Vechazar venikav
kemotzi zayit. Then it got another hole right near the old one,
also the size of an olive. וסתמו. Usetamo. And you filled that
up. עד שהשלימו למוציא רמון. Ad shehishlimo lemotzi rimon. Until now it
has so many little holes right next to each other that had
you not filled them up, sequentially, you would have a big hole
the size of a pomegranate. So you got the idea? At no
time did you have a hole bigger than the size of an
olive, but if you would have taken off all of your fixes,
all the holes would have combined to the size of a pomegranate.
Okay. So what's its status? מהו? Mahu? Does that lose its טומאה,
tuma, because do we look at it based on what it would
have been had you not filled it up?
So אמר ליה רבי יוחנן. Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says to him, רבי שנית לנו. Rebbi, shnisah lanu. You
taught us, סנדל שנפסקה אחת מאזניו ותקנה. Sandal shenipsaka achas me'aznav vesikna.
If one of the straps break and you fix it, טמא מדרס.
tamei midras. נפסקה שנייה ותקנה. Nipsaka shniya vesikna. The second strap broke
and you fix it. טהורה ממדרס אבל טמאה מגע מדרס. Tahora mimidras
aval tmeia maga midras. It's no longer מדרס, midras, but it touched
מדרס, midras, as we discussed before. But the point is, it's not
the old shoe. ואמינא לך. Ve'amina lach. We said to you, מה
שנא ראשונה דאיכא שנייה? Ma shna rishona d'ika shniya? Why is it
when the first one breaks it's still
טמא? tamei? Because the second strap is still around. שנייה נמי דתקנה
ראשונה? Shniya nami d'tikna rishona? When the second strap broke,
the first strap had already been fixed. There was never a time,
right, when it stopped being a shoe. So why should it lose
its
טומאה? tuma? ואמרת לן עליה פנים חדשות באו לכאן. Ve'amarta lan aleia
panim chadashos ba'u l'chan. No, new faces have come here. It's true
it never stopped being a shoe, but since all of the critical
parts have been replaced, it's a new shoe and therefore doesn't have
the old
טומאה. tuma. הכא נמי פנים חדשות באו לכאן. Hacha nami panim chadashos
ba'u l'chan. Since all of the, if you had not done any
fix, it would have had a big hole, so a critical thing
has been removed and replaced, although sequentially, so it's a completely new
vessel. So, oh, that was such a brilliant connection. קרי עליה. Kari
aleia. So he said about him, לית דין בר אינש. lais dain
bar inash. Oh, this is not a normal human being, this is
a מלאך. malach. איכא דאמרי. Ika d'amri. Some say כגון דין בר
אינש. k'gon dain bar inash. Oh, this is a real מענטש, mentsch,
this is a real person. Okay, so anyway, but a very nice,
a very beautiful praise. ואמר רבי זירא. Ve'amar Rabbi Zeira. And רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira said, because of that, of comparing him, oh, he's
like a מלאך malach or this is a real person, אמר רבי
זירא אמר רבא, Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rava, a very famous statement,
אם ראשונים בני מלאכים אנו בני אנשים. im rishonim bnei malachim anu
bnei anashim. If the earlier ones were like angels or children of
angels, anyway, we're just people. ואם ראשונים בני אנשים אנו כחמורים. V'im
rishonim bnei anashim anu kachamorim. And if they were like humans, what
a human is supposed to be, we're like donkeys. ולא כחמורו של
רבי חנינא בן דוסא ושל רבי פנחס בן יאיר. Velo kachamoro shel
Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa veshel Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair. Not like a
special donkey like the donkeys of רבי חנינא בן דוסא Rabbi Chanina
ben Dosa or של רבי פנחס בן יאיר. shel Rabbi Pinchas ben
Yair. Those were donkeys that they were very careful, they wouldn't eat
some food that wasn't theirs. You know, those were very special. אלא
כשאר חמורי. Ela kishar chamorei. No, we're just like סתם stam donkeys.
Now, I want to say a couple of very important things about
this interesting thing. First of all, this idea of replacing every component
part so at the end all the parts have been replaced. So
does anybody, has anybody heard of, yeah, let me get the right
name for it, the Ship of Theseus? Theseus? No, Theseus. No? So
this was a, this was called, or sometimes it's called Theseus's paradox.
It was recorded by Plutarch, and the issue was that this was
a philosopher, Theseus, and he asked the question, the following question. If
you have a ship... that you've replaced every single plank sequentially. One
plank broke you replaced it, the next plank broke you replaced it,
the next plank broke you replaced it, and at the end of
the day all the planks have been replaced over time, is this
the same ship as the ship you started with?
And people also cells, so they're
like every seven years you have all new cells. Oh that's a
good point. So anyway you could look this up in Wikipedia, this
has been like this type of question was asked or they say
sometimes it's asked as Washington's axe, or Lincoln's axe. You know, if
the handle has been replaced three times, the head has been replaced
two times, is it still the same axe? Right, but at no
time was all the pieces replaced at once. So this is a
really you know serious philosophical question about
identity. And here's really what the גמרא's Gemara saying. It's saying that
in that case coming out on one side of it, if you
replace enough of the component parts so that had those parts all
been missing at once, it would have stopped being the object, then
those the fact that it has those new component parts makes it
have a new identity. So that's actually quite interesting and you know
it ties into broader philosophical questions. Now I want to also say
something about the ראשונים Rishonim and the אחרונים Achronim because this fits
into also a larger theological discussion and idea about ירידת הדורות, Yeridat
HaDorot, right, which is that all the generations, you know, the earlier
generations were great, afterwards everybody, you know, is on a lower מדרגה
madrega and everybody gets further and further away from הר סיני Har
Sinai to a lower and lower מדרגה madrega and it's this you
know just like complete you know almost like you know worship of
of of the past. Now obviously there has to be you know
profound you know veneration and respect for the past גדולים gedolim but
the question is is whether this is you know whether we you
have to buy into a particular philosophy that like later generations are
nothing compared to earlier generations, which is a you know a sense
that this גמרא Gemara comes up with. So there's a very nice
book on this called by Menachem Kellner called Maimonides and the Descent
of the Generations, ירידת הדורות, Yeridat HaDorot, where he basically says that
this idea of ירידת הדורות Yeridat HaDorot was you know definitely like
it was promoted by certain גאונים, Geonim, but it by no means
is you know deep like like like the canon, the the you
know the רמבם Rambam never never quotes it. The רמבם Rambam actually
in some ways says you know explicitly even rejects it in certain
areas like by science he says you know okay חזל Chazal made
mistakes by science that was what they were they were limited more
limited than we were you know we made more advances in science.
You know and then it gets into a broader question and there
are other גמרות Gemarot that don't say this you know say something
that suggests the opposite of this idea, or not the opposite but
certainly not necessarily exactly you know this idea of of ירידת הדורות.
Yeridat HaDorot. So and he says it really gets to a question
of of where you think the authority of תורה שבעל פה Torah
She-ba'al Peh derives from. Is do you need is it central to
your religious philosophy the authority of תורה שבעל פה Torah She-ba'al Peh
that the earlier generations were the holiest and the most brilliant ever
and that's why we have to listen to them? If that's why
we listen to them then then you can never you know raise
any questions about you know what... Well A it's paralysis of moving
forward and B it's also that like you can never you know
never disagree, never raise any questions, you know it's it becomes more
than just respect and veneration it becomes like a worship. And therefore
if there are problems like they're contradictions with science and other types
of things you have to shut them out because you need the
past to be perfect and to be on a much higher מדרגה
madrega than nowadays. But that doesn't have to be your basis of
תורה שבעל פה. Torah She-ba'al Peh. Your basis of תורה שבעל פה
Torah She-ba'al Peh could be because you believe that the Torah empowers
בית דין, Beit Din, you know a central בית דין Beit Din
and maybe somehow that that got transferred to the authority of the
גמרא, Gemara, but it becomes because like the Supreme Court. You don't
have to think that the earlier Supreme Court were the biggest גדולים
gedolim to explain why it's law. It's law because they're the body
that's empowered. So it's the body that was empowered and it doesn't
have to be because through this fact that they were that you
know that they were perfect and we're nothing. So this is a
really important you know question of an attitude towards the authority of
תורה שבעל פה Torah She-ba'al Peh and חזל Chazal and to people
interested I'd advise you to read the book by Menachem Kellner called
again Maimonides and the Descent of Generations. Yes.
Yeah I was thinking of my earlier point, like what I was
saying before, like you took your shoe and the shoemaker replaces the
sole. Right. Yeah same thing as a new shoe. So if a
נדה niddah had worn it and then she- she- yeah. Exactly.
In Japan sometimes there's a building that's like a special shrine or
a special his- I don't know if they still do this or
a special historical place. Every 100 years or so they completely rebuild
it.
But in their minds it's the same, it's the same.
Right, right. And the the fact that it's not as old as
the history says it is is irrelevant.
Right, right. So that's well how about the Spanish Portuguese
synagogue? They'll tell you they've been around in the United States since
whenever 350 years. Right, is it even the same materials? I I
I
that's also the question. Somebody somebody did a twist on the on
this Ship of Theseus question which is so let's say you take
every plank and you're removing it but no no no you're taking
it off the ship and you're replacing it one by one... one,
and then after you have all of the planks you rebuild a
new ship. So which one, if either, is the original ship?
There's actually a controversy with an original ship in Baltimore like that.
The first USS Constellation was built in 1797. Right. The current one
looks to have been a new ship built with the planks of
the old ship in 1850.
There you go.
It leads to a lot of confusion.
Okay, there you go. So let's now see if we can get
through the Mishnah. ונודות יין ושמן. v'nodot yayin v'shemen. Now, other things
you can do are like, you know, like flasks, whatever, you know,
pouches, whatever you call them, like a leather flask. A flask. Canteen?
Canteen, whatever. Anyway, of wine and oil, you know, that they had
like a, like a rope on the top to cinch the neck.
פשיטה, pshita, of course, again, it's regularly done and undone. לא צריכה
דאית ליה תרתי אוני. lo tzericha d'is lei tartei uni. It has
two basically, like, you know, ears. מהו דתימא, ma d'teima, חדא מינייהו
בטולי מבטיל לה, chada minnai bitulei mivatel lah, קא משמע לן. kamashmalan.
So it's possible to like undo one of the straps and still
pour out wine from it, you know, even though normally you would
undo both. So same type of point before, so we're not concerned
even though it would be possible that you would leave one there.
קדרה של בשר, kdeirah shel basar, a pot of meat that apparently
they would put some type of leather on it, tie something on
top of it. פשיטה, pshita, obvious. לא צריכה דאית לה שלוחא. lo
tzericha d'is lah shlucha. Of course what exactly שלוחא shlucha means, some
have a different גירסא, girsa, but again, it's some type of a
spout. מהו דתימא בטולי מבטיל לה, ma d'teima bitulei mivatel lah, so
maybe you wouldn't untie the cover because you could pour the thing
out of the spout. קא משמע לן, kamashmalan, we're not concerned about
that. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר קושרה. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer
koshrah. So Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says, what'd he say?
He said,
oh yeah, you can tie a rope in front of an animal,
in front of the pen. So obviously there again, the animals would
go in and out of the pen on a daily basis, you
weren't going to leave it there. So the Gemara says, פשיטה, pshita,
that's obvious. So, no, לא צריכה דאית ליה תרתי אסיסי. lo tzericha
d'is lei tartei asisei. There are two knots. Now Rashi says either
it means that there are two ropes, one on the top, one
on the bottom, or you tie the rope on both ends, right?
It's not that the rope was tied to one post already and
you just tied it to the other. You actually tied the rope
on both ends. מהו דתימא, ma d'teima, I might think, חדא מינייהו
בטולי מבטיל. chada minnai bitulei mivatel. You'll leave one of the knots
in place, or if it had two ropes, you'll leave one of
the ropes in place. קא משמע לן kamashmalan that we're not concerned
about that. Maybe it'll happen, but it won't normally happen and we're
not concerned, and therefore it's not a permanent knot. אמר רב יוסף
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. amar Rav
Yosef amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. We
rule like him, that that's okay, even the rope on the pen.
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, הלכה מכלל דפליגי? halacha miklal d'pligi?
So are you suggesting that they argued? Maybe they never argued, maybe
he was just adding another example. אמר ליה, amar lei, מאי נפקא
לך מינה? mai nafka lach mina? What difference does it make? If
we rule like him, who cares if they were arguing about it?
So אמר ליה, amar lei, גמרא גמור זמורתא היא? gemara gemar zi'mureta
hi? Right, we had that before, which is like, we have a
teaching and you want to turn it into a song? So it's
important to know everything, even if it's, you know, it's not just
a relevant הלכה למעשה. halacha l'maaseh. We want to understand what the
issues were, maybe it'll give us better insight into what the debate
was about, what different parameters were about. So, and with that we
will end and continue with next Gemara.